Elmer Gertz Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Speeches and Writings File, 1888-1990 (Box 381-465)
  - Writings, 1888-1990 (Box 383-465)
    Papers relating to Gertz's writings are divided into three categories: articles, books, and other writings. Papers relating to his articles are arranged chronologically; book files are organized alphabetically by title; and other writings are arranged alphabetically by type of manuscript. Unidentified writings and writings by individuals other than Gertz are filed last in the series.
    *Microfilm shelf no. 13,575
    - By Gertz (Box 383)
      - Articles
        - 1935-1949, (3 folders)
        - 1951-1960, (8 folders) (Box 384)
        - 1961-1964, (7 folders) (Box 385)
        - 1964-1973, (7 folders) (Box 386)
        - 1974-1988, (11 folders) (Box 387)
        - Undated, (8 folders); (6 folders); (4 folders) (Box 388, Box 389, Box 390)
      - Books
        - The Best of Frank Harris: An Anthology (unpublished), (3 folders) (Box 391)
        - Charter for a New Age: An Inside View of the Sixth Illinois Constitutional Convention (1980)
          - General, (4 folders); (5 folders) (Box 392)
          - Various drafts, (1 folder); (7 folders) (Box 393, Box 394)
        - Chicago Tribune manuscript (unpublished)
          - Correspondence, 1928-1981, (4 folders)
          - Research material
            - General, (5 folders)
            - Keeley, James (Box 395)
              - Correspondence
                - 1898-1920, (11 folders)
                - 1921-1933, undated, (12 folders) (Box 396)
              - Harding, Warren G. (Box 397)
              - Miscellany, (4 folders)
              - Printed matter, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 398)
              - Speeches, (4 folders)
              - Writings, (1 folder); (5 folders) (Box 399)
            - Linn, James Weber
            - Printed matter, (2 folders); (3 folders) (Box 400)
          - Various drafts, (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 401)
        - Clown of Glory (unpublished), (2 folders)
        - Cold Fire (unpublished)
        - Cynic's Progress: The Life and Longings of Charles A. Dana, the Man Who Hated Presidents (unpublished)
          - Bobbs-Merrill Co.
            - Correspondence, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 402)
            - General
          - Research material
            - Dana original manuscripts
            - Dana's Christmas Eve (printed version)
            - General, (4 folders); (6 folders); (7 folders) (Box 403, Box 404, Box 405)
          - Various drafts, (3 folders); (8 folders); (7 folders); (2 folders) (Box 406, Box 407, Box 408)
        - Death Row: A Look Into Capital Punishment, (unpublished), (3 folders)
        - For the First Hours of Tomorrow: The Illinois Bill of Rights (1972)
          - General, (3 folders); (5 folders) (Box 409)
          - Various drafts, (4 folders)
        - Frank Harris: A Study in Black and White (1931) (Box 410)
          - Correspondence
            - 1923-1929, (10 folders)
            - 1930-1933, undated, (9 folders) (Box 411)
          - Miscellany
          - Research material
            - General, (1 folder); (5 folders) (Box 412)
            - Original manuscripts by Harris
              - Correspondence, 1888-1930, undated, (5 folders)
              - Miscellaneous, undated
              - Pantopia, undated
            - Scrapbooks, (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 413, Box 414)
          - Reviews, 1931-1932, undated
          - Subject file
            - Butler, M. B., 1929-1930
            - Contempo, 1931-1932, undated
            - De Casseres, Benjamin, 1929-1932, undated
            - Douglas, Alfred Bruce, 1922-1933, undated, (2 folders)
            - Dunn, Waldo H., 1930-1933, undated
            - Eastman, Max, 1919, 1930-1934, undated
            - Goldberg, Isaac, 1926-1934, undated
            - Heymoolen, Anton, 1929-1932, undated
            - Hubbart, Dwight, 1926-1930, undated
            - Johnson, Harold R., 1931-1934, undated
            - Newman, Ernest, 1924-1932, undated
            - Rosenberg, Leo, 1930-1934, undated
            - Sinclair, Upton, 1928-1934
            - Smith, Byron Caldwell, 1929
            - Snyder, H. M., 1931-1936, undated
            - Stephens, Kate, 1898, 1929-1934, undated, (2 folders) (Box 415)
            - Tobin, A. I., 1927-1934, undated, (7 folders)
          - Various drafts, (1 folder); (8 folders) (Box 416)
        - Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.: The Story of a Landmark Libel Case (1992) See also Containers 15-17, same heading, (7 folders); (3 folders) (Box 417, Box 418)
        - Goss v. Lopez (unpublished), (4 folders)
        - A Guide to Estate Planning (1983), (1 folder) (Box 419)
        - A Handful of Clients (1965)
          - Correspondence, (5 folders); (3 folders) (Box 420)
          - General, (4 folders); (2 folders) (Box 421)
          - Various drafts, (6 folders); (7 folders) (Box 422, Box 423)
        - Henry Miller: Years of Trial and Triumph, 1962-1964: The Correspondence of Henry Miller and Elmer Gertz (1978) (Box 424)
          - General, (4 folders)
          - German translation
          - Research material, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 425)
          - Various drafts, (2 folders); (6 folders) (Box 426, Box 427)
        - Moment of Madness: The People vs. Jack Ruby (1968) (Box 428)
          - Follett Publishing Co., (7 folders); (2 folders) (Box 429)
          - General, (5 folders)
          - Research material (Box 430)
            - Disqualification of judge
            - General, (6 folders)
            - Trial of Jack Ruby, by John Kaplan and Jon R. Waltz, (5 folders) (Box 431)
          - Various drafts, (2 folders); (6 folders); (7 folders); (4 folders) (Box 432, Box 433, Box 434, Box 435)
        - Odyssey of a Barbarian: The Biography of George Sylvester Viereck (1979)
          - Correspondence
            - A-F, (5 folders)
            - G-Z, (11 folders) (Box 436)
            - Unidentified
          - General, (2 folders) (Box 437)
          - Research material
            - General, (7 folders); (6 folders); (4 folders) (Box 438, Box 439, Box 440)
            - Johnson, Neil M., (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 441)
            - Viereck, Edwina, diary
            - Viereck, George Sylvester
              - Correspondence
                - 1903-1930, (7 folders)
                - 1931-1936, (9 folders) (Box 442)
                - 1937-1959, undated, (9 folders) (Box 443)
              - Diary, 1901 (Box 444)
              - Freud, Sigmund, letters and messages of Freud to Viereck, 1923-1936*
                * Available on microfilm only. One reel, accession number 13, 575.
              - Handwritten drafts of manuscripts
              - Typescripts of manuscripts, (6 folders); (7 folders); (1 folder) (Box 445, Box 446)
            - Viereck v. United States, (2 folders)
          - Various drafts, (4 folders); (7 folders); (8 folders) (Box 447, Box 448, Box 449)
        - Quest for a Constitution: A Man Who Wouldn't Quit: A Political Biography of Samuel Witwer of Illinois (1984) (Box 450)
          - General, (6 folders)
          - Various drafts, (1 folder); (7 folders) (Box 451)
        - Sandburg: An Informal and Unofficial Pictorial Study (unpublished)
          - Correspondence
            - 1945-1963, (2 folders)
            - 1964-1966, undated, (6 folders) (Box 452)
          - General, (2 folders) (Box 453)
          - Printed matter, (5 folders)
          - Various drafts, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 454)
        - The Short Stories of Frank Harris: A Selection (1975)
          - General, (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 455)
          - Various drafts, (6 folders)
        - To Life: The Story of a Chicago Lawyer (1974) (Box 456)
          - General, (2 folders)
          - McGraw Hill Book Co., (3 folders)
          - Proposal
          - Research material, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 457)
          - Various drafts, (6 folders); (7 folders); (1 folder) (Box 458, Box 459, Box 460, Box 461)
      - Other
        - Correspondence
          - 1932-1974, (11 folders)
          - 1974-1988, undated, (7 folders) (Box 462)
        - Letters to the editor, 1951-1990, undated
        - Miscellany, 1965-1990, undated, (2 folders)
        - Pamphlet regarding the Chicago Tribune, 1942, undated, (3 folders)
        - Poetry, 1927-1928, undated (Box 463)
        - Prefaces and introductions, 1961-1975, undated, (3 folders)
        - Reviews
          - Drafts
            - 1951-1978, (5 folders)
            - Undated, (1 folder); (7 folders) (Box 464)
          - Printed copies
            - 1945-1969, (1 folder)
            - 1970-1984, undated, (4 folders) (Box 465)
    - By others, 1949-1964, undated For additional material see Containers 466-467, Manuscripts and printed matter by others, (4 folders)
    - Unidentified, undated
- Miscellany, 1789, 1860-1991 (Box 465-468)
  Correspondence, memoranda, calendars, original manuscripts and printed matter collected by Gertz, financial papers, academic papers, biographical material, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by topic or type of material.
  - Academic file, 1926-1931, undated (Box 465)
  - Awards and honors
    - Decalogue Society of Lawyers, 1961, 1972-1973, (1 folder) (Box 466)
    - General, 1950-1991
  - Biographical, 1950-1954, 1977, undated
  - Calendars, 1958, 1965, 1975-1990, (3 folders)
  - Manuscripts and printed matter by others
    - Dana, Charles A. See Containers 401-408, Cynic's Progress
    - Harris, Frank See Containers 410-416, Frank Harris
    - Herman, Samuel G.
      - Book draft, undated
      - Correspondence, 1949-1963, undated, (7 folders) (Box 467)
      - Miscellany, 1957-1963, undated
      - Scrapbook, 1928-1930, undated
    - Hirschfield, Magnus, 1914, 1930-1934
    - Howe, Julia Ward, 1862-1885, undated
    - Keeley, Gertrude, undated
    - Keeley, James See Containers 395-399, Chicago Tribune manuscript
    - Miscellany
      - Manuscripts, 1883-1885, 1894, 1902-1949, undated
      - Printed matter, 1789, 1860-1866, undated
    - Viereck, George Sylvester See Containers 441-445, Odyssey of a Barbarian
    - Wolseley, Garnet Joseph, 1880-1899, undated
  - Miscellaneous, 1955-1963, undated, (2 folders) (Box 468)
  - Mississippi real estate, 1954-1955, (2 folders)
- Addition, 1921-1997 (Box 469-484)
  Correspondence, memoranda, family papers, legal files, subject files, speech material, articles, book reviews, background information, photographs, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
  Arranged by type of material according to the arrangement of the main portion of the papers.
  - Family papers (Box 469)
    - Gertz, Laurence (nephew), and family, 1973-1995, (4 folders)
    - Gertz, Mamie (wife), 1961-1968, 1990-1995, undated
    - Other relatives, 1961, 1967-1968, 1992-1996, undated, (2 folders)
  - General correspondence
    - 1962-1992, (8 folders)
    - 1993-1997, undated, (21 folders) (Box 470)
  - Legal file (Box 471)
    - Personal
      - Gertz v. Bass, 1964
    - Professional
      - Baruck, John, 1970-1971
      - Crump, Paul, 1993
      - Finton, William, 1968
      - Howell v. Dash
        - Background information, 1982-1993, undated, (2 folders)
        - General case material, 1993, (3 folders)
      - Illinois v. Dermer, 1964
      - Illinois v. McCauley, 1993-1995, (2 folders)
      - Kostrubala, Thaddeus and Ingrid, 1965-1967, (3 folders) (Box 472)
      - Lande, Gilbert, 1972
      - Meyer v. Seamans, 1971-1972
      - Miscellany, 1974-1984, 1993
      - Pancotto, Sam, 1968-1971
      - Tropic of Cancer, Grove Press v. Morris, 1961
      - United States v. Green
        - Background information, 1921-1974, undated, (2 folders)
        - Correspondence
          - 1973, (2 folders)
          - 1974 (Box 473)
        - Court documents, 1972-1974, (5 folders)
        - Press, 1973-1974
      - United States v. McClure See same container and Container 472, United States v. Green
      - Wold v. Wold Air Brush Mfg., 1977-1980, (6 folders)
  - Subject file (Box 474)
    - American Jewish Congress, 1993-1995
    - Anastaplo, George, 1989-1994
    - Blind Service Association
      - 1991-1993, (10 folders)
      - 1994
        - Jan.-Aug., (2 folders)
        - Sept.-Dec. (Box 475)
      - 1995-1996
    - Caxton Club, 1990-1997, (2 folders)
    - Clarke, Arthur C., 1982-1993, (4 folders)
    - Connaughton, Daniel E., 1985
    - Decalogue Society of Lawyers, 1990-1995, undated
    - "Defending Our Civil Liberties," educational videotape produced by Paula Grace, 1994
    - Gertzman, Jay A., 1992-1997, undated, (2 folders)
    - Harris, Frank, 1935, 1953-1956, 1986, 1993-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 476)
    - Irons, Peter, 1981-1989, (4 folders)
    - Kennedy, John F., assassination, 1988-1994, undated, (4 folders)
    - Logan, John
      - 1985-1990, (3 folders)
      - 1991-1995, (2 folders) (Box 477)
    - Lovitz, Gene, 1981-1992
    - Manuscript Society News, 1994-1996
    - Marks Jewish Orphanage Home, Chicago, Ill., 1991-1993
    - Martinetti, Ronald
      - 1975-1979, (5 folders)
      - 1980
        - Jan.-July, (2 folders)
        - Sept.-Oct. (Box 478)
      - 1981-1995, (6 folders)
    - McNew, Rose, 1994
    - Meyer, Russ, 1973, 1983-1995, (3 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1980, 1992-1995, undated (Box 479)
    - Netch, Dawn Clark, 1993-1994
    - Press about Gertz, 1934, 1943-1944, 1990-1996, undated
    - Rosten, Leo, 1935, 1979-1980, 1990-1997, undated, (2 folders)
    - Ruby, Jack See Container 476, Kennedy, John F., assassination
    - Shargel, Charles, 1992
    - South America, 1978-1991, (2 folders)
    - Sparling, Edward J., 1980
    - Tesla, Nikola, 1993-1994
    - Verson, Karol, 1993-1995, undated
    - Viereck, Peter Robert Edwin and George Sylvester
      - 1924-1925, 1936, 1944-1945, 1980-1989, (5 folders)
      - 1990-1996, (2 folders) (Box 480)
    - Wawszkiewicz, Edward J.
      - 1973-1987, (8 folders)
      - 1988-1993, (2 folders) (Box 481)
  - Speeches and writings file
    - Speech file, 1988-1996, (3 folders)
    - Writings by Gertz
      - Articles, 1967, 1988-1996, undated, (2 folders)
      - Books
        - Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.: The Story of a Landmark Libel Case (1992)
          - Advertising and promotion, 1992-1993
          - Correspondence, 1978-1979, 1988-1994, (4 folders)
          - General, 1986-1994, undated, (3 folders)
          - Reviews, 1992-1993 (Box 482)
          - Southern Illinois University Press, 1979, 1989-1993, (3 folders)
          - University of Illinois Press, 1978-1989, (4 folders)
        - To Life: The Story of a Chicago Lawyer (1990), 1990-1994, (4 folders)
      - Other
        - Festschrift for George Anastaplo, 1976-1992, (2 folders)
        - Letters to the editor, 1991-1997, undated
        - Miscellaneous, 1995-1996
        - Prefaces and introductions, 1990-1991
        - Real Crime Book Digest (Box 483)
          - Articles, 1993-1995, undated, (6 folders)
          - General, 1993-1995, undated, (3 folders)
          - Reviews, 1993-1995, undated, (3 folders)
        - Reviews, 1992-1994
  - Miscellany
    - Awards and honors, 1993-1996, (2 folders)
    - Calendars
      - 1992-1993
      - 1994-1995 (Box 484)
    - John Marshall Law School, Chicago, Ill., 1973-1974, 1992-1996
    - Travel, 1992-1995, (4 folders)
- Oversize, 1957, 1967 (Box OV 1-4)
  Oversize material consisting of broadsides, a scrapbook, and copies of design plans.
  Organized and described according to the series, boxes, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Legal File (Box OV 1)
    - Professional
      - Novel v. Garrison
        - Press
          - Scrapbook, 1967 (Container 192)
      - Novel Books, Inc. (Box OV 2)
        - Novel Books v. City of Chicago
          - Background information, undated (Container 192)
      - Watson v. Sparkman & Stephens, Inc. (Box OV 3)
        - Background information
          - Plans and specifications
            - 1964 (Conntainer 273)
            - 1965 (Container 274)
  - Subject File (Box OV 4)
    - Darrow, Clarence
      - General, 1957 (Container 318)
Appendix: Legal Abbreviations
Administrat [ive, ion] Admin.
Administrat [or, rix] Adm'[r,x]
Agriculture Agric.
America [n] Am.
Associate Assoc.
Association Ass'n
Atlantic Atl.
Authority Auth.
Automobile Auto.
Avenue Ave.
Board Bd.
Brotherhood Bhd.
Brothers Bros.
Building Bldg.
Central Cent.
Chemical Chem.
Commission Comm'n
Commissioner Comm'r
Committee Comm.
Company Co.
Consolidated Consol.
Construction Constr.
Cooperative Coop.
Corporation Corp.
Department Dep't
Development Dev.
Distribut [or, ing] Distrib.
District Dist.
Division Div.
East [ern] E.
Education [al] Educ.
Electric [al, ity] Elec.
Electronic Elec.
Engineer Eng'r
Engineering Eng'g
Enterprise Enter.
Environment Env't
Environmental Envtl.
Equipment Equip.
Exchange Exch.
Execut [or, rix] Ex'[r,x]
Federal Fed.
Federation Fed'n
Financ [e, ial, ing] Fin.
Foundation Found.
General Gen.
Government Gov't
Guaranty Guar.
Hospital Hosp.
Housing Hous.
Incorporate Inc.
Indemnity Indem.
Independent Indep.
Industr [y, ies, ial] Indus.
Institut [e, ion] Inst.
Insurance Ins.
International Int'l
Investment Inv.
Liability Liab.
Limited Ltd.
Litigation Litig.
Machine [ry] Mach.
Manufacturer Mfr.
Manufacturing Mfg.
Market Mkt.
Marketing Mktg.
Metropolitan Metro.
Municipal Mun.
Mutual Mut.
National Nat'l
North [ern] N.
Organiz [ation, ing] Org.
Pacific Pac.
Product [ion] Prod.
Public Pub.
Railroad R.R.
Railway Ry.
Refining Ref.
Road Rd.
Savings Sav.
Securit [y, ies] Sec.
Service Serv.
Society Soc'y
South [ern] S.
Steamship [s] S.S.
Street St.
Surety Sur.
System [s] Sys.
Tele [phone, graph] Tel.
Transport [ation] Transp.
University Univ.
Utility Util.
West [ern] W.